I would love to do it if I did had some
time I can do it somebody else fundraise
I can translate but you know I didn't
think I would but I'm so interested in
them I think I could do it now if I just
had time it's very difficult ok let's
start then of course Buddha says but if
you take all these people to Nirvana
you don't take anybody to Nirvana ok
that's where the trouble starts ok if
you take all these different beings to
Nirvana nobody reaches Nirvana
then master Kamla she is like yay we
finally reached the point you know
coaching emptiness
Lord Buddha finally reached the real
meaning of the Sutra emptiness ok when
when you reach nirvana nobody reaches
Nirvana okay then he's so happy master
come here then it goes off on a long
thing if you don't understand emptiness
you can't do anything you can't become a
Buddha you can't reach nirvana
you also can't make money have a good
relationship have good health have peace
of mind and you can't help the world
he's just like a DCI teacher okay now he
goes to one by one he says you won't
ever have prosperity you will never have
good relationships you will never be
healthy you will never have peace of
mind and you cannot help the world
if you don't understand emptiness and
that's why Buddha went straight to
emptiness
in in in course 15 ACI it's called
tonguing
this is the knee meets that's what
Buddha really wants to talk about
everything else is just filler okay he
just wants to talk about emptiness okay
so so that the next meditation you have
is is to think about how it's going to
help your financial how it's going to
help your health how it's going to help
your relationships how it's going to
help your inner peace of mind and how
it's going to help you help the world
you need and Kamala Sheila repeats
exactly what some copper was saying last
week you know all those six perfections
of a bodhisattva do them with
understanding emptiness they are
perfections do them without
understanding emptiness that you're just
a nice guy and it's gonna wear out okay
so it's very clear and master commercial
is very excited for example with just
with your finances okay if you
understand the emptiness of money why
are you gonna be successful when you
have money in your hand and you
understand it you understand it came
from giving so what do you want to do
with it yeah okay it's just like so
simple you know like a Buddhist I added
two towards money is completely
different from another person's attitude
to us you know other people are thinking
I don't have four thousand dollars to
pay for this orange juicer then a
Buddhist is thinking okay I'll do it
nada I won't try I'll do it you know why
I'm just gonna get more come on you know
it's like the smartest investment you
can make is to give it away okay all
right so on a positive on a positive
sign if you understand emptiness
generosity is easy because you
understand where money comes from the
mean you get
you like hot potato no I got I gotta get
rid of this I gotta give this to
somebody because I enjoy it I can use it
I can buy diamond mountain the orange
juicer $4,000 orange juice like I'm
excited you know I got a chance to buy
from for dime mountain I'm like wow how
great you know they're not next week
it's just gonna Morris come to people
put money my bag just collects money now
I just gave her some big words that she
hid it already it's a big bag of money
and I'm like I don't and I'm like
getting counted let's get rid of it you
know so son in a positive way it's nice
now let's go to the negative way okay
which the next photo in your meditations
is by the way that's the luminous pin
that's picture about the two pens the
first one it's the little picture of a
pen that came out of their karmic seed
in your mind okay the first one what I
call the luminous pen is the little
picture of a pen that came out of your
karmic scene okay and then it became a
pen okay so now you know what that
picture is what's the next picture yeah
it's - its - it's a couple having an
argument okay
it's a man and a woman having your
argument okay so this is the famous DC I
seen that we do on the stage that's how
I learn fun phone that's how I learned
the word
someone call me a phantom on the stage
it means you're tired you work hard you
come home you're hoping your husband is
in a good mood and will give you a nice
hug and you open the door and the
husband starts screaming at you because
you didn't make dinner you know actually
you worked late you were buying
groceries and you came home and you're
tired and you're hoping he's gonna give
you a nice huh but instead he starts
screaming at you
why didn't you prepare dinner
a Buddhist at that point has to
understand there are two husband's in
the room there are two husband's in the
room okay in in philosophical terms
making doc you get down and it has a are
Cucuy make doc you give that okay the
gear is spelled are gyu meaning cars but
in this case it means cause to be so
there's one there's two husband's in the
room when whenever you feel tense
whenever you feel anger whenever you
feel friction with somebody else there
are two you're facing two people one is
you get duck when it's made you make it
dark means the one who's not there
really the one who's not there really
okay the you get doc is the one who is
there there's always two any time you
have a negative emotion there's two of
the person you're looking at always okay
make it darkness the one who's not there
how do we describe the one who's not
there yeah I like that
yeah he's young at me for no reason all
it's one word right for no reason at all
he's I just got home I was working all
day all I did was open the door and he
starts screaming at me for no zero
okay for no reason at all okay no reason
no I didn't I didn't do anything I
didn't do anything you know I just got
home I just opened the door you know I
didn't do anything yeah I didn't do
anything it's nice at all
it's like two words you know I dunno
anything okay then the husband who yells
at you because you didn't do anything
doesn't exist never existed cannot exist
and will never exist in the future all
for impossible totally impossible okay
it's not my fizz not I didn't do
anything you know okay that kind of
husband isn't there and that the
terrible tragedy and irony of life is
that every time you ever felt upset on
anybody you were upset at nobody they
weren't there okay you can't be upset
unless you think someone's there who
cannot be there okay it's very terrible
it's very terrible you know all of the
suffering in the world comes from
phantoms things that we're never there
couldn't be there we're not there we'll
never be there okay
a husband who's I didn't with him it's
my fault
okay there's no such husband why he's
popping out of a seat in your mind like
the pen in the last picture a luminous
little husband's coming out of your mind
who planted the seed in your mind I did
how did you plan it Nick in that DCI
story remember yeah you yelled at your
kids last week okay you said mom has to
go to work early she has to be at work
at 8:00 please be ready at 8:00 please
be ready at 7:45 - you told your kids
you walk in the bedroom
they're jumping on the bed they're still
in their pajamas
and you say you are the stupidest kids
in Guangzhou you're the stupidest kids
in Guangzhou then you plan a karmic
scene a week later you come home and
poison all the end of the story is how
do you prove that you're stupid if you
want to prove you're really stupid what
will you do then no you stupid okay then
you plant another seed then next week
the kids are bad again and that's called
okay
Sentara isn't this grand rebirth twelve
part wheel son Cyrus taking place many
sensors in your life are many wheels are
happening Wheel of Life are happening
every day you know your husband's
yelling because you the other kids you
yell to cut husband should you is he
stupid he is but don't say it because
then you have to see another stupid
husband okay if you don't like stupid
husbands don't don't answer don't say
something bad okay
it's okay to sitting down when things
that come down and say look you know
it's okay to explain what happened you
know I was at this door you know I had
to take the kids to the doctor I didn't
have time to make dinner please don't
yell at me that's fine that's okay
that's alright
whether it works or not
depends on whether you've been
reasonable lastly okay but it's still
good to give a reasonable explanation
to take an aspirin when you're sick okay
if it works a lot we don't know it
depends on
were you reasonable last week okay but
it's not wrong to say look it hurts my
feelings when I open the door and you
yell at me but when things are calm down
explain yourself
but whether explanation works or not is
going to depend on whether you were
reasonable last week it's all cycles
okay so who do you take to Nirvana
nobody meaning the job for a Nirvana
sizer is to find people who are
suffering and get them out of suffering
we say people are who are fettered
people have the chains of suffering
those are the people yelling at their
husbands you know okay those people who
are in Chains who are still creating
cycles we say they are chained they're
in jail that's the next photo okay it's
a guy in jail okay
I think his hands are hanging out yeah
okay so a person who wants to be a
Buddha and help other people reach
nirvana has to find people who don't
know about the husband thing and they
should go on tours around the world and
try to give as many people as they can
in the room and tell them about that the
husband was never there that that's what
a buddy sought with us just try to get
people to understand but they have to
find people who are in the jail of
thinking they should scream back at the
husband and who think that it was for no
reason at all that the husband yelled at
them okay but who created those people
yeah you got understand okay when you
save somebody the reason you're seeing a
person who's ignorant is because you're
ignorant
okay if you were never ignorant you
would be me upon London nepo nah then
it's the definition of the paradise body
everything it's the definition of
paradise body Buddha fixed five things
are fixed okay one thing they're always
surrounded by Pleasant high-level
Bodhisattvas why because they are okay
if you yell at the kids you'll be
surrounded by yelling husbands if you're
perfectly enlightened person you'll be
surrounded by enlightened people
okay so when the Bodhisattvas trying to
take some help somebody they got to
understand that the reason they're
seeing somebody who's reacting wrongly
is that they did it for so long themself
okay but they're saving somebody they're
trying to get somebody out of the jail
of samsara but at the same time they
understand that this person's coming
from them okay and then you can be a
real buddy suffer Maha Bodhisattva okay
there's a big debate in kamila Sheila do
lower schools have Bodhisattvas do
Hinayana schools have bullies office he
says yes why you said why because Bodhi
means enlightenment right sattva means a
seeker of enlightenment right stop that
literally literally means it has two
meanings but one is courage Safa means
courage that's why they called in
Tibetan charges Sembach bomb is power
Paul means virasana vieira warrior okay
so do lower school practitioners have
courage to try to reach their own
enlightenment their tracks enlighten yes
so he says they are buddy service that's
why the body suffers in the diamond
cutter cetera always called maha
Bodhisattvas
okay they want to reach enlightenment
for everybody okay which brings me to my
next subject while you're helping those
people if you conceive of them do che
write that if you conceive of them as
people you we can't call you a body
somewhere who okay while you're helping
those people if you think of them as
people I'm not even gonna call you buddy
something I can't call you buddy
okay that's really confusing okay like
I'm supposed to help somebody but I'm
not supposed to think of them as a
person okay and then MasterCard machine
that goes off he goes off on it okay
because Buddha says he mentions three
things he says if you see them as a as a
conscious being you're nobody somewhere
I'm not gonna call you if you see the
people you're helping as a conscious
being I not call you a Buddhist you're
not a bodhisattva when nobody's going to
call your body something if you see them
as a conscious being that's in Tibetan
stem chain which the sanskrit is cetera
okay but it's a different set that's
that that means an existing being a
thinking being okay if you see them as a
septa you nobody suffer then he says if
you see them as a Jeeva if you see the
message IVA a living being soaked the
sutra says soak if i had translated it
into tibetan i would have used a
different tibetan word called soak chart
which means a living being
it's soak is confusing he it's not i use
here
it's Jeevan like Jeevan Mukti living
okay living person okay so if you think
there if you see a person and you
believe they're a thinking being and you
try to take them to Nirvana you're
nobody suffering if you see a person and
you think they're a living being and you
try to take them to Nirvana you nobody
suffer last one if you think there are
put kala
if you think they're a person an
individual you're nobody said well okay
then come I see less like so happy
because he's in his element you know
this is what he's been waiting for you
know now he discusses three ways in
which a person is not a person he
discusses three ways in which a person
is not a person
he doesn't directly tie them to those
three different sanskrit words thinking
being living being individual being but
i think we can we can do we can do it i
think it must be an earlier source okay
there's one reason why a thinking being
is not a thinking being there's a second
reason why a living being is not a
living being and there's a third reason
why an individual being is not an
individual being okay so he gives three
so I'll give you the three and then we
can stop in like 10 minutes 15 minutes
then the punchline comes tomorrow which
means you have to come back tomorrow no
it's okay you should have some tension
in the teaching sometimes you should
confuse the student because when you
when they figure it out they feel so
happy there's a drama to it it's very
it's a good way to teach you shouldn't
tell all the answers it's not a Buddhist
way let them figure it out okay so I'll
give you the three questions the first
one starts with the picture of the guy
in the jail number
13 okay Buddhism says uh Nachman
Buddhism says uh not men
there is no micro okay there is no
permanent self pending separate Michael
okay there's no such thing
Buddhism says no such thing there's no
like crystal invisible thing called
Michael okay in three senses there's no
Michael first sense because the non
Buddhists say there isn't Michael okay
independent Michael okay what what does
that mean we'll get into it okay but but
the Buddhist Buddha stood up and said
there's no Michael then the other guys
freaked out
they're like well okay there's three
problems were done number one how does
the Michael who was in that jail or
sansara becomes the Michael who's
outside the jealous and Sarah if there's
no Michael you know in in 2016
Michael is in the prison of samsara he's
still yelling and his partner and saying
no he's at all okay
and then he works works hard works hard
he goes to Diamond Mountain he does many
retreats on his own and then sudden he's
outside of the jail since our right are
they connected
are they is it still Michael okay the
guy who got Nirvana the guy who went to
Nirvana due to the efforts of some other
buddies Samba right is it still Michael
then if it is then how if there's no
Michael if there's no permanent separate
lasting individual independent Michael
then how could the guy who was still in
sin scientist 2016 who got to Nirvana in
2019 what connects them if there's no
Ockman if there's no Michael if there's
no independent Michael then why isn't it
Fred in 2019 you know you could just
become somebody else suddenly if there's
no Michael that that stretches from one
to the other then then why isn't it
gilsu
you see in 2019 just turned out to gal
stay you know what keeps you Michael
what made you Michael what kept you
Michael who connects the Michael who was
incensed her to the Michael who got out
what connects them okay if there's no
Michael if there's no independent thing
called Michael what connects them okay
that's the first conundrum the first
question okay
second what's the picture next picture
post man I love this picture
it took me so long to takes me so long
to find these pictures post man I always
think you know I live in Rimrock Arizona
it's a little bit bigger than Bowie me
and my friends once we sat in a
convenience store I said we were we were
having a soda rhythm I said just for fun
let's count how many bottles of beer
leave this place while we're waiting
it was 420
and we were there for like 20 minutes
and 30 minutes okay that's where I live
and so and the post office is a junk
okay
they won't even deliver mail to my house
because I'm on a dirt road so they say
you can't have mail delivery you know so
you know and if so sometimes just as a
joke you can write a letter to Geshe
Michael I can write a letter to Geshe
Michael say you're stupid okay then I
fold it up and I go to the post office
in delivered then I don't know in
Rimrock
maybe ten days later the guy will come
to your house suppose you have mail
delivery and he says I have a letter for
you you know and you say thank you you
know and you open it up what does it say
you're stupid and and and if we are
stupid we get angry at the postman why
did you bring me in this letter you know
you stupid you know you the worst
postman and me run a milling Reuben you
know why did you bring me this letter
okay that's like yelling at your husband
okay
he's just the postman who wrote the
letter you did when the y'all had two
kids
you did when you yelled at your kids
he's delivering to you the letter which
you wrote to yourself okay but we yell
at the postman right that's why I put a
postman okay who's the postman every
person you were ever anger at in your
whole life was a postman
they were just delivering you your own
letter that you wrote to yourself last
week when you called your husband stupid
last week although he is stupid I'm
agree but don't saying okay if you don't
want the letter okay
now personally I would connect the first
one right Michael who was in jail on the
Michael who got out to the to the
statement that if you think a thinking
individual if you think you're taking a
thinking in the
to Nirvana you're nobody Sutter I think
he's talking about the first one the the
connection between the guy who was in
jail and the guy who got out of jail
what connects them if there's no micro
second one was Jeeva living being okay a
living being the one he has a new word
it doesn't exist anywhere in the
scriptures he calls chapel and xalapa do
solvable that's uh I've made great
efforts to see so yeah then he calls it
the doer and the eater the doer and the
eater the door is the one who wrote the
letter the ear is the one who received
the letter in he made up a new language
for it you know doer was two weeks ago
you yelled at somebody eater
is the person who got yelled at two
weeks later
okay you're both you're the doer and
you're the eater
it means you use you mail the Karma and
you receive the Karma okay
he calls it chip up Osama PO it is very
confusing and they carved it wrong they
put sub-sub more profound or something
they misspelled it that's that's how
hard it is to translate so there's the
the person who commits the Karma
you know pushes somebody on the bus and
then the person who gets hit by some
money too much later okay what's what's
the guy going to ask Buddha yeah who
connect them if there's no Michael then
Michael can push somebody on the bus and
Gayle say we'll get punched by somebody
two weeks later okay if there's no
Michael if there's no permanent lasting
independent solid
thing called Michael then who connects
those two connected how come I always
get back what I did how come I don't get
back what you didn't you seeing I mean
oh I can't word pick the last bad karma
I did and it goes to him why can't the
deed you know why is the connection to
have to come to me if there's no Michael
this is who's saying this the opponent
the questioner they're questioning what
is this diamond cutter suitor stuff you
know what's the confusing yeah what do
you mean you can mail a car man and
receive it if there's no Michael you
know what are you talking about Lord
Buddha you take someone to Nirvana but
you don't take a man your mana so who's
the connection between the eater and the
doer
okay got it we're almost done third
question which i think relates to the
third part of the last part of the sutra
which was about an individual being
booed Galah individual being because
they said when you take somebody to
Nirvana
you don't take any merit in your honor
and if you think you do you're not a did
he say that did he say that you're not a
buddy stuff but did he say that he said
something more subtle yeah yeah we can't
name your buddy stomper we can't call
your buddy something that's also
emptiness right what is naming meaning
Buddhism karmic seed opens picture comes
out goes onto the thing the pen pen
picture comes out karmic seed opens Ken
picture pops out goes on the person
that's called naming so it's very
profound that he doesn't say you're
nobody suffer he says I can't call you a
boy suffer it's very profound he's
talking about emptiness all again
okay so third one then I can go home and
have something delicious then as a child
you you brought up by your parents you
know and your mom like takes care of you
you know like you you hurt your knee
your mom takes care of you you have a
class photo your mom makes you a new
dress you know like your mom takes care
of you when your kid right then you grow
up you go away to college you know you
start living in New Jersey and you know
you see your mom every 10 years or 12
years or you don't come home very often
you see them 10 years later after you go
to college or something in America we
don't stay so close to our parents
most people they they go to high college
they say goodbye and then make you see
them once a year or once every three
years or something not every New Year's
okay so the other guy says to come with
Sheila you saw your mother when you're a
child you come back home how do you
recognize her how do you recognize her
that's my mom there's three women in
your house when you come home you're
like mom okay like how do you recognize
your mother if there's no Michael if
there's no connection between the person
that that mom helped him when he got
hurt and then 20 years later he comes
home and he sees three women and he says
to one of them Oh mom it's so good to
see you how can he recognize her okay he
asked two questions one is yeah how do
you recognize things and how do you
remember things so the third one has two
parts how do you remember things and how
do you recognize things you know how do
you say mom thank you for helping me
when I hurt
when I was a little kid how do you how
can there be a remember rare of an
incident when you're a child if there's
no Michael okay because according to you
nobody goes to Nirvana when they go to
Nirvana okay okay the other guys
complaining they want to have a Michael
who's like real and exist out there and
this independent of other stuff you know
Michael eats but they're still Michael
Michael loves but there's still Michael
you know Michael goes through
experiences year after year but that's
still Michael
then they there's a feeling in the human
heart that there are there must be a me
which is like a ball you know like a
permanent thing and then things happen
to it and you know they meet people they
love people they lose people things
happen to it but there's a ball there's
a there's a Michael who's permanent
lasting independent okay that idea is
the cause of all suffering according to
Buddhist and that ideas that cause of
our suffering
it doesn't mean by the way that there's
no soul or no spirit the living mind of
Michael is infinite into the past and
into the future it's infinite there is a
Michael who lasts forever yeah I mean
there is one thing which is like a soul
or spirit there is such a thing and that
exists but we the one we're thinking
about is different okay it doesn't come
from how I treat other people it's
independent things happen to it it loses
things that come out things in
but it's permanent okay but yeah you
continue forever you will never stop and
you have no beginning but which came
first the chicken or the egg okay yeah
you've seen everything you've done
everything you've been everything you've
been Miss America not not billions of
times count countless time okay
countless times alright you've been
everything you've been Hitler you've
killed millions of people countless
times okay but who is that who is that
me where does it come from how can we
make it enlightened okay we'll talk
about it tomorrow what connects the
person who was in jail to the person who
got free in Nirvana what connects the
doer to the either of the Karma and what
connects the incident when you're a kid
to the remembering it or recognizing
your mom later yeah who connects them
who is Michael what's what is Michael
really where does Michael really come
from okay and we'll talk about it
tomorrow all right
but meditate on this I think you have
six new meditations if you don't count
the Buddha in the sky fine five
thank the it's the first one no there
was some huh
oh yeah what's the first one today all
the pen okay
yeah emptiness is the only thing that
matters and then there's no second
husband in the room and then three
questions of connection to record those
those come together if you want to have
fun today at home take the diamond
cutter Sutra and figure out where we are
because we are following it very closely
and we will we will only get to a corner
of this this week okay and I would love
to do it again we should go through the
whole thing you know but this is Sir the
first quarter just the first quarter but
you figure out which meditation relates
to each statement here okay
and you'll see that we're following it
very closely okay but it's not obvious
okay all right then you're gonna know
that diamond kind of sutra better than
anybody in China knew the diamond cutter
Sutra for about 500 years seriously
okay and then you should teach it to
other people and the way to teach it is
with the pictures you know they look
like just pictures but they're following
the Sutra very closely they're following
the meaning of the suit are very very
closely so you today at home before you
meditate on one of the pictures say
where does that picture fit in here and
you you'll find it and then you can
teach it to other people
you could teach the real meaning of the
oldest book in the world